grief is a fascinating process and it is
we are not well served in thinking about
it by the degree to which depictions of
grief are so far from the mark there is
a way in which things like grief and
dreams are depicted very badly in
fiction and so we we tend not to have a
clear conscious relationship with our
own grief experience we'll go through it
and then we'll even forget what it's
like but I would argue that grief a it
is clearly an adaptation as difficult as
it is to face most creatures don't face
grief they lose an offspring or you know
a partner and they move on you know a
cat that loses a kitten mother this is a
kitten
can't really afford to miss a beat
because you're probably other kittens
and so anyway they don't show grief in
the same way that some creatures do but
certain creatures do show grief and the
group of creatures that shows grief is
very interesting so we we see grief in
chimpanzees we see it in elephants
obviously people dogs and what I would
argue this tells us is that there's
something about highly intelligent
highly social creatures that causes
grief to effectively be reinvented each
time because we and elephants and dogs
and chimpanzees don't all share some
ancestor from which we've inherited
grief maybe we do with chimps but dogs
and elephants would be a totally
separate pair of evolutions
so why would this debilitating state
evolve adaptively in creatures that are
highly social and highly intelligent and
what is the state now the first thing to
realize is think about the way a funeral
actually is rather than the way it is
typically depicted the funeral involves
people often somber but not always in
the same room in a funeral you will see
even the closest kin of the person who
has been lost laughing talking about
mundane trivialities and crying all of
these things exist together and the
experience of grief is one in which one
will face intense periods of reflection
and sadness interspersed with everyday
experiences interspersed with periods of
having completely put aside this
incredible loss and that period will go
on for months it goes on actually rather
intensely if you've lost somebody close
for a full year
in fact the Jewish tradition involves
not placing a headstone until a year has
passed after the burial which I've
always thought was and
an indicator of something significant
about it having gone through a full
year's worth of holidays and
celebrations and seasons without the
person that has been lost before one
memorializes or memorialize was fully
but in any case I will argue that grief
is the downside of love and what I mean
by that is when you love somebody you
prioritize them in your mind sounds
trivial almost but you prioritize them
in your whole conscious schema you
expect them at certain places and times
you depend on them you integrate them
into your understanding of the world and
when they are lost
you have to unintegrated that doesn't
mean that you forget them but it does
mean that to the extent that somebody
was very important to you that that
expectation has to be excised from your
active program so that you do not
continue to expect them so that you do
not depend on them when they can no
longer show up if in the terrible
circumstance that it it's your child
that you've lost you can no longer live
with the same obligations in other words
let's say that you've lost a child but
you have other child's you have to
reschedule everything in what you
understand based on the reality that the
child that you had banked on investing
in over their life is no longer in need
of your help and your other children are
so I would argue that to the extent that
we love somebody that they are deeply
woven into our our own program and the
unweaving process cannot be simple if it
was simple than the relationship that we
had with that person couldn't have been
very deep in the first place so if the
relationship was deep the unweaving of
that person
to be deep and I would argue that the
pattern of grief that we experienced
where you have these intense periods of
anguish that are interspersed with
periods of normalcy and that the periods
of anguish become farther and farther
apart but they don't become less fraught
until finally they do that that is
emblematic of the fact that your brain
keeps discovering places that the person
who has been lost was wired in and at
first you find all of the obvious ones
all of the circuits that become active
regularly it becomes apparent that oh
this is caged and that has changed and
as time goes on the remoteness of the
circuitry that the person was connected
to grows and so their frequency with
which you encounter one of those
circuits goes down and so in this way
the person finds their memory
recategorize so that you no longer are
depending on them in a living way so I
agree it is neither a full excision nor
a full transformation you know there was
there aspects of whoever this person was
that are no longer relevant after
they're gone right one doesn't need to
deal with their dietary restrictions for
example after they're gone so there's no
point in really even remembering what
they were necessarily on the other hand
their insight might be very valuable and
so one might take what one expects of
this particular person's view on the
world and they might build it into an
internal structure that they can access
so for example I know my grandfather was
very important to me and
he taught me a lot about how to build
things and he was very he got a
reputation as a safety nut but he wasn't
a safety net what he was was very good
at anticipating how things fail so that
he could engage risks and not have it
come back to haunt him and he
transferred this to me you know he would
he would give me a hint about what he
thought I was doing wrong and how it
might end up coming back to hurt me and
when he died I remember noticing that it
was as if a ghost followed me up the
ladder every time I went up a ladder to
do some work on some electrical
component or building something and I
remember it's a very young person like a
boy I think he warned me about the
danger of people leaving things on top
of ladders and I know that when you move
a ladder you if somebody has left
something up there whether it was you or
somebody else when you move the ladder
you tend to tilt it back towards
yourself and if it's a hammer and you've
left it up there it'll fall right on
your head and so one doesn't think about
this when one goes to put something down
you're up a ladder you don't have enough
places to put things
it's very natural to put things on that
top space and then to forget that they
were there you go down the phone is rung
your cup of coffee is ready whatever you
go down and then you realize you need to
move the ladder and you've forgotten
what you've left up there so somebody
needs to build an extra circuit that
checks about what's up there and am I
really safe to move the ladder am i
certain I didn't leave something heavy
up there or something that could fall on
my eye or something like that and so I
have the sense when I interact with a
ladder that my grandfather's there in
particular and that he sort of throws a
little elbow my way and says it you know
you sure that ladder is clear before you
go and move it we were pushing a little
far here but is your grandfather just
information after he's done or is there
like a presence is there a distinct
intimacy that persists between you and
this person who's gone that that
overcomes like that time death period
yeah I don't think this isn't troubling
to me at all I'm comforted by the fact
that it's not it's not like my
grandfather has become a safety robot
that you know the barn bell goes off
when I interact with the ladder I'm
comforted by the fact that my
grandfather isn't really gone that he's
been taken you know internal and I like
the idea that he looks through my eyes
and that things that he never he didn't
live to see that you know in some sense
I can let him see things that he might
have been fascinated by or if I go
somewhere in the world he never went and
you know I can sort of allow him to see
it you know and it's one can torture
oneself with you know how literal is
this the answer is well it's not really
literal at all on the other hand maybe
it is because at the same level that you
know I am the conscious me but I am also
the unconscious me and the unconscious
me is aware of things that the conscious
me isn't and so you know I can torture
myself with whether I'm one people or
several and you know among the several
there are the people that I've cared
about and lost and in any case it's also
comforting to me that you know if
presumably I will die before my children
do and they will have known me very well
and I feel some comfort in the idea that
as long as they live that some aspect of
the part of me that mattered will still
wander the earth with them just know
your dietary restriction right my
dietary restrictions I'm happy to take
them with me the whole prediction of
this hypothesis is that griefs extent
will be predicted by certain
characteristics okay that the surprising
nature of a death to the extent that
somebody was really not expected to die
because they were young because they
were healthy or something like that
makes grief all the more in
because you didn't do any of the work
ahead of time to the extent that
somebody is old or infirm you may have
grieved enough by the time they're gone
that there's no work left to do and that
can actually result in people having
guilt over the fact that they haven't
grieved somebody that they believed they
cared very deeply about and frankly we
need to free ourselves from that because
if somebody's been really sick and so
your brain knew they were gonna go and
it prepared by doing the work ahead of
time it's not that you didn't agree if
it's that you've already grieved and so
you can't say how much you cared about
the person tells you how much you're
gonna grieve because some of the grief
can happen ahead of time so you know the
degree to which somebody is important to
you can actually create weird phenomena
the number of people who intensely
grieved John F Kennedy for example
who've never met him and never would
meet up right what did that have to do
with well in some ways John F Kennedy
was present in their living rooms week
in and week out okay and he was
important he had an effect on the way
the world function and so it wasn't much
different than losing an important you
know elder in the community in some
unexpected way there are two big
categories there are people that you
depended on whose loss changes really
your prospects and there are people who
depend on you and their loss changes
your obligations and it is interesting
how similar in some ways those two kinds
of grief are it's interesting that at
least in English we don't have two
different words for maybe other
languages do but you know and you can
see this in the extreme with pets the
loss of a pet does not change
what you know what you who you can
depend on in in the extreme case maybe
you know a dog that has a particularly
important role in some work relationship
might change your prospects but in
general the way we have pets these days
the loss of your dog exquisitely painful
as it is is not a big loss in terms of
what you're capable of doing you can get
another dog for one thing but in some
ways they take on the role of you know
they're not children but they take on
that role for some people they actually
substitute for children and so their
loss is much more shocking and painful
than people expect who haven't been
through it so anyway those are two big
categories people you depend on people
who depend on you or people or pets that
depend on you those things are both very
painful and then the question of the you
know the Entertainer or something David
Bowie dies and his people my age at
least who paid attention to him feel
some terrible sense of loss and you know
that in one way is is a novelty
phenomenon you know we wouldn't have had
access to some iconic distant figure
that we would never have met who
contributed to our lives on the other
hand he really did contribute to some of
our lives and it's not so surprising
that when somebody who has created
mental architecture right exploring some
parameter you know Major Tom meant a lot
to many of us and the loss of the
creator of that idea somebody who gave
us a window into this sort of
existential angst of an astronaut and
its relationship to drug addiction and
all of that that those were really rich
powerful concepts that enhanced life for
many of us and to know
that the unique mind that created those
things won't be creating any more of
those things is it is a real loss even
if we never mend them
so here's the problem actually there is
a bomb-proof way to get people to
remember how to pronounce Weinstein but
I can't use it why not is it - it causes
problems what it causes bigger problems
than it solves
indeed well at least you're smart enough
to take your advice thing I guess
what's the secret if I kind Stein with a
w oh yeah you just can't say it's like
Einstein you know yeah it sounds bad but
let me the bagel company like the bagel
company I think you just solved the
problem dude